<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Medicine &#8211; Alif-dental</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../index.html</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2019 14:01:20 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6.2</generator>

<image>
	<url>./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/11/Logo120by120-1.jpg</url>
	<title>Medicine &#8211; Alif-dental</title>
	<link>./../../../index.html</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>How to get rid of a toothache at night</title>
		<link>./../../../2019/11/14/audio-post/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../../../2019/11/14/audio-post/index.html#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[BoldThemes]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2019 14:01:20 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Prevention]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medicine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Toothache]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://showcase.bold-themes.com/home-made/?p=287</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A toothache is a painful annoyance, especially at night. Getting a toothache at night can make falling asleep or staying asleep very difficult.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>However, there are a number of remedies that may help people find relief and get to sleep, including taking pain relievers or applying a cold compress or even cloves to the tooth.</p>
<p>In this article, learn more about nine home remedies for relieving a toothache at night.</p>
<h3>6 ways to treat a toothache at night</h3>
<p>Treating a toothache at night may be more difficult, as there is not much to distract a person from the pain.</p>
<p>However, people can try the following methods to relieve pain:</p>
<h4>1. Oral pain medication</h4>
<p>Taking over-the-counter (OTC) pain medications such as acetaminophen (Tylenol) or ibuprofen (Advil) is a quick, simple way for many people to effectively reduce mild-to-moderate toothaches.</p>
<p>Always stay within the recommended dosage on the packaging.</p>
<p>If the toothache is severe, it is best to see a dentist and speak to them about stronger pain relievers.</p>
<h4>2. Cold compress</h4>
<p>Using a cold compress may help ease the pain of a toothache.</p>
<p>Applying a bag of ice wrapped in a towel to the affected side of the face or jaw helps constrict the blood vessels in the area, which can reduce pain to allow a person to fall asleep.</p>
<p>Applying a cold compress to the area for 15–20 minutes every few hours in the evening may also help prevent pain when going to bed.</p>
<h4>3. Elevation</h4>
<p>Pooling blood in the head may cause additional pain and inflammation. For some people, elevating the head with an extra pillow or two may relieve the pain enough for them to fall asleep.</p>
<h4>4. Medicated ointments</h4>
<p>Some medicated ointments may also help reduce toothache pain. OTC numbing gels and ointments that contain ingredients such as benzocaine may numb the area.</p>
<p>However, benzocaine is not suitable for use by young children.</p>
<h4>5. Salt water rinse</h4>
<p>A simple salt water rinse is a common home remedy for a toothache.</p>
<p>Salt water is a natural antibacterial agent, so it may reduce inflammation. This, in turn, helps protect damaged teeth from infection.</p>
<p>Rinsing with salt water may also help remove any food particles or debris stuck in the teeth or gums.</p>
<h4>6. Hydrogen peroxide rinse</h4>
<p>Periodontitis is a serious gum infection that generally occurs as a result of poor oral hygiene. It can cause issues such as soreness, bleeding gums, and teeth that come loose in their sockets.</p>
<p>The author of a 2016 study found that rinsing with hydrogen peroxide mouthwash helped reduce plaque and symptoms of periodontitis.</p>
<p>People should always dilute food-grade hydrogen peroxide with equal parts water. Swish the solution in the mouth, but do not swallow it.</p>
<p>This remedy is not suitable for children, as there is a risk they may accidentally swallow the mixture.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../../../2019/11/14/audio-post/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
