<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Health &#8211; Alif-dental</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../index.html</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2019 09:53:33 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6.2</generator>

<image>
	<url>./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/11/Logo120by120-1.jpg</url>
	<title>Health &#8211; Alif-dental</title>
	<link>./../../../index.html</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Xylitol: Uses, effects, and possible benefits</title>
		<link>./../../../2019/09/27/xylitol-uses-effects-and-possible-benefits/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../../../2019/09/27/xylitol-uses-effects-and-possible-benefits/index.html#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[BoldThemes]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2019 09:53:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Interesting]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Prevention]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Teeth]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Xylitol]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://showcase.bold-themes.com/home-made/?p=234</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Xylitol is a lower-calorie sugar substitute with a low glycemic index. Some research suggests that it may also improve dental health, prevent ear infections, and possess antioxidant properties.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Xylitol is a sugar alcohol, which is a type of carbohydrate and does not actually contain alcohol. Xylitol occurs naturally in small amounts in fibrous fruits and vegetables, trees, corncobs, and even the human body.</p>
<p>Manufacturers use xylitol as a sugar substitute because its sweetness is comparable with that of table sugar but with fewer calories.</p>
<p>Xylitol is a common ingredient in many products, from sugar-free chewing gum to toothpaste. People also use xylitol as a table-top sweetener and in baking.</p>
<p>In this article, we look at the uses and potential health benefits of xylitol. We also cover its side effects, drug interactions, dosage, and alternatives.</p>
<h3>Uses</h3>
<p>Xylitol has a similar level of sweetness to sugar but with a fraction of the calories. It is a popular ingredient in a variety of products, including sugar-free gum and toothpaste.</p>
<p>Manufacturers add xylitol to a range of foods, including:</p>
<ul>
<li>sugar-free candies, such as gum, mints, and gummies</li>
<li>jams and jellies</li>
<li>honey</li>
<li>nut butters, including peanut butter</li>
<li>yogurt</li>
</ul>
<p>Xylitol is also an ingredient in some dental care products, including:</p>
<ul>
<li>toothpaste</li>
<li>mouthwash</li>
<li>other fluoride products</li>
</ul>
<p>Xylitol sweeteners are available to purchase online.</p>
<h3>Potential benefits</h3>
<p>Xylitol has several potential health benefits, including:</p>
<h4>Low glycemic index</h4>
<p>Xylitol has a low glycemic index (GI). This means that consuming it does not cause spikes in blood glucose or insulin levels in the body. For this reason, xylitol is a good sugar substitute for people with diabetes.</p>
<p>Due to its low GI, xylitol is also a weight loss-friendly sugar substitute.</p>
<p>Also, a 2015 study revealed that xylitol had significant blood glucose-lowering effects in rats that ate high-fat diets.</p>
<h4>Dental health</h4>
<p>Xylitol is an ingredient in many dental hygiene products, including toothpaste and mouthwash. This is due to the fact that xylitol is non-fermentable, which means that the bacteria in the mouth cannot convert it into the harmful acid that causes tooth decay.</p>
<p>The oral bacterium Streptococcus mutans is largely responsible for plaque, which is the sticky, white substance that can accumulate on the outside of a person&#8217;s teeth.</p>
<p>Plaque binds lactic acid against the surface of the tooth. This acid breaks down the enamel and leads to tooth decay.</p>
<p>While it is normal for people to have some plaque on their teeth, excess amounts can lead to tooth decay, cavities, and gum disease.</p>
<p>A 2017 systematic review suggests that xylitol reduces the amount of S. mutans bacteria in the mouth, which reduces the amount of plaque and may help prevent tooth decay.</p>
<p>A 2014 study examined the effects of xylitol on Porphyromonas gingivalis, which is the bacterium responsible for gingivitis, or gum disease. If left untreated, excess amounts of P. gingivalis can move into the bloodstream and lead to systemic inflammation.</p>
<p>In the study, scientists grew samples of P. gingivalis in a laboratory and added them to human cell cultures pretreated with xylitol. They saw that xylitol increased the production of immune system proteins and inhibited the growth of the bacteria.</p>
<h3>Side effects and safety</h3>
<p>The United States Food and Drug Administration (FDA) have approved xylitol as a food additive. Xylitol is generally safe, but like other sugar alcohols, it can cause digestive issues such as bloating and diarrhea in some people.</p>
<p>It is worth noting that xylitol can be very toxic to dogs. It is vital to store products containing xylitol in a safe place that pets cannot reach. Anyone who thinks that their dog has consumed xylitol should call their veterinarian or the Animal Poison Control Center immediately.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../../../2019/09/27/xylitol-uses-effects-and-possible-benefits/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
